Test 2. This is the IELTS listening test. You will hear a number of different recordings
and you will have to answer questions on what you hear. There will be time for you to read
the instructions and questions and you will have a chance to check your work. All the
recordings will be played once only. The test is in four parts. At the end of the test you
will be given 10 minutes to transfer your answers to an answer sheet.
Now turn to part 1. Part 1. You will hear a woman who is caring for
her elderly mother talking to a friend. First you have some time to look at questions 1
to 4. Now listen carefully and answer questions 1 to 4.
It's really good to see you Tom. Since I had to give up work I feel I'm losing touch
with my friends and colleagues. We really miss you in the office. We were all so sorry
you had to leave. But you must be relieved to have more time to look after your mother.
How is she? Well she's very cheerful but she needs a lot of help. Have you tried to get
any support from the local council? No, I didn't know I could. Yes, they offer different
kinds of practical support. They realise that carers sometimes need time for all the other
responsibilities they have apart from the person they're caring for and also that they
sometimes need a break. Absolutely. Okay, so tell me more. How do I go about getting
this support? Well you'd have to have an assessment of your mother's needs. That means someone
would come round and talk to you about the situation and what you need. So for a start
they'd want to know the amount of time you spend looking after your mother every day.
Okay. Then they'll probably ask you what sorts of tasks you do for your mother during the
day. Things like if she needs help with getting dressed for example. Right, I help her with
that and also I help her get into the shower in the morning. Yes, that sort of thing. They'll
probably ask you if you do the shopping for her and help her at mealtimes and whether
she can cope using money. Yes, that's becoming a bit of a problem. She used to be very good
at it but not anymore. Before you hear the rest of the conversation you have some time
to look at questions 5 to 10.
So recently I've noticed she's started to have quite bad problems with her memory. If
I wasn't there I think she'd forget to eat for example. And often she doesn't seem quite
sure what day it is. Yes, tell them about that. And are there any physical difficulties
you have caring for her? Lifting her for example. Yes, she's quite heavy and I'm afraid of hurting
my back. I'd be in real trouble if that happened. They can give you advice about that and also
about how to avoid the possibility of your mum having a fall. Great. So once they've
done this assessment, if I'm eligible, what happens next? Well, they might support you
financially. So they might help you with transport costs, like if you have to get a taxi to take
your mother for an appointment for example. I usually drive her myself actually. So could
I claim for the petrol? You could. And you can claim for the insurance too. Oh, right.
And if you need help with the housework they can arrange for someone to come along once
or twice a week. And one other thing, I hope you don't mind me saying this, but it's important
you look after yourself and it seems to me you're under quite a bit of stress. I am, yes. Well,
tell the council because they may be able to give you some advice on how to minimise it. Really?
Though actually I feel so much better having talked to you. I'll get in touch with the
council straight away. Now, shall we go for coffee or something?
That is the end of part one. You now have one minute to check your answers to part one.
You now have one minute to check your answers to part one.
Rwy'n gobeithio y byddwch chi'n gwybod beth sy'n digwydd yng Nghymru.